okay
um so the last piece of lecture is about
uh is about this this is Monte Carlo uh
why Monte Carlo because Monte Carlo has
a famous Casino
um and so when people talk about
algorithms that rely on uh random
samples uh they call them Monte Carlo
algorithms
um and so we're going to talk about
Monte Carlo tree search
uh so Monte Carlo research
um was mostly developed for the purpose
of playing go
um because go has a big branching factor
and if you just try to do alpha beta
search with a fixed Horizon you can only
get to about depth four four and a half
uh in go and that's completely useless
and um
so Monte College research has two key
ideas uh one of which is very sensible
and one of which is like
completely bizarre uh so I'll tell you
the completely bizarre one first okay so
to evaluate a position
uh in Monte Carlo research or MCTS
uh so if a position is a state s
what you do is you play a whole bunch of
games from that position in your head
right so you're simulating these games
um but you're playing those games using
uh what's called the roller policy which
could be as simple as choose a random
move and in fact the earliest
implementations which were successful uh
did exactly that they just chose a
random move uh and then you know so one
player chooses randomly the other one
two issues randomly just take turns
playing around the moves and then you
see
who wins and uh you count so for each of
those many many rollout games you just
add up how often you win and lose and if
you win a lot starting from State s that
means that state s is good and if you
lose a lot that means State s is bad
okay and this is a to me very very
counter-intuitive idea but it turns out
to work surprisingly well
um
the second idea which I think is
perfectly reasonable is that we abandon
this idea of a fixed Horizon so rather
than saying okay
here's the Horizon and you're only
allowed to search within that
um we say oh no you know I think this is
really interesting so I'd like to search
this part of the tree
um and completely ignore all of that lot
right so go away go away I just want to
look down here right uh because all
those other moves are just obviously
stupid
um and this is the only part of the tree
that's interesting okay so this is
selective search and clearly this is
what humans do you can you can have a
human chess player sort of Speak Out
Loud speak their thoughts out loud and
and uh some of the stuff is a bit
inscrutable but a lot of the time they
say well I'm thinking about this but
that that that that that that that and
in the time they have available they
might be looking at a hundred
possibilities maybe a couple hundred
um
and so they can't possibly be building a
big fat tree they have to be looking
down a relatively small number of paths
uh and uh and getting lots of useful
information from that because they have
really good intuitions about what's
likely to happen in the game
okay
so uh let me just show you a rollout
right this is a this is a go position so
for those of you who play go uh I don't
need to explain it very much
um but this happens to be a very famous
position called move 37 well the move in
this position is called move 37 this is
a mystical move that alphago played
against Lisa doll
um and that's the move right there so
black went in that square and when uh
when alphago played there
um all the professional go players who
are watching
assume that you know alphago had blown a
fuse this is a completely terrible move
that you know only a beginner would make
and maybe not even a beginner would make
such a stupid move
um
and I'm not going to go into exactly why
it's stupid because actually turns out
not to be stupid but I think what they
thought was well you basically you know
so in go you're trying to capture
territory and white is obviously
building territory over here
um and I think they thought well you
know white can just close off the
territory by going in that in that
square
um and then you know black is going to
be stuck in in White's building a
fortress and blah blah so this was seen
as a very very weak move okay so what is
a rollout a rollout just means okay well
it's whites turns neck so so black in
choosing this move is thinking ahead
okay uh let's see what happens
if I do this move but I look ahead using
sort of moral as a random place so uh I
say well maybe White's gonna go there
well maybe I'm going to go there White's
going to go there you just play a bunch
of random moves oops and um
uh and then uh you get you know you do
that I'm not going to go all the way to
the game because that'll be another
couple of probably 290 something moves
um
but you go uh you go all the way to the
end of the game and then you just see
who won see who has the most territory
uh see whose pieces have been captured
uh and then you're done okay
so that's uh that's a rollout and then
when you're done you record the result
either black wins or white wins and uh
and then you do that hundreds of times
uh play hundreds of games and then the
fraction of wins turns out in practice
to correlate pretty well with the true
value of the position not perfectly but
pretty well
another advantage of this method
is that on Modern Hardware gpus you can
run all these rollouts in parallel so if
you're going to do a thousand roll outs
a thousand play a thousand simulated
games you can just take uh you know a
thousand GPU threads and do rollouts in
each one and then add up the results
okay so that's rollouts
it does help the random play is okay but
not great you might want to do a little
better so anything you can do to improve
the rollout policy will typically give
you more accurate results but of course
you don't want to make the rollout
policy the thing that chooses the moves
expensive because then it's going to
take too long to do all those rollouts
so you have to find something that's
quick dirty and a little bit better than
random and that's fine
okay so now we've got this idea of
rollouts um then here's version zero of
the algorithm right we do uh n roll outs
from each child so this is the root here
the children so we're going to do let's
say 100 roll outs from each child uh and
then we just record the fraction of wins
so we got 57
roll outs 57 wins out of 100 uh if we go
this way we got 39 if we go that way and
we got 65 if we go this way so we would
choose to go to the right and
and that so that was the first
generation of Monte Carlo research go
programs uh and it actually turned out
to be a significant improvement over the
sort of handcrafted sometimes rule-based
with a little bit of search thrown in
add hot kinds of programs that had been
built for the previous 30 years or so
okay uh now let's look at this case
right so uh we got 57 wins here zero
wins here and 59 there so you might say
okay great well I'll probably go this
way but I'm a little bit less sure
because 57 and 59 are pretty close uh
but the thing that you should notice
when you look at this case is that zero
out of a hundred
why did I do a hundred rollouts
for a position where obviously this is a
terrible position because by the time
I've done about 10 rollouts and I've got
zero out of ten
I should be saying look this is a waste
of time why am I using my rollouts my
computation my scarce resource uh to
convince myself that this movie is
really terrible when I already am
convinced that it's really terrible okay
um so the the next versions of uh what
you call it research
actually take the
rollouts and allocate them to the more
promising nodes so you might do a little
bit of rollouts for each one but when
you find that one of them is really
terrible you stop allocating search to
that
and you move the allocation to the other
nodes so here after the first 10 moves
we said okay to hell with that we're
going to reuse so we've got nine we've
got 90 more rollouts to spare
um so we're going to get 40 of them to
here and 50 of them to there and
um and I think if I remember correctly
90 out of 150 is uh is a little bit
better than 77 out of 140 and so we have
more confidence because we've done more
rollouts we've got more confidence that
going to the right is a better move okay
so that's the next thing right allocate
your rollouts to more promising notes
okay what about this case
right so we did 10 for this for the one
in the middle and we won six times we
did a hundred for here and we won 61
times
so what would you do next right if you
had one more rollout to do where would
you put it right would you put it on
this one which is the most promising has
the highest win percentage probably not
because you say look I'm already
fairly confident in what the win
percentage for that node is going to be
um but here I still have a lot of
uncertainty because I've only done 10
trials
so
you're allocating results not just to
more promising nodes but also to nodes
that are more uncertain so it's a
trade-off between how promising is it
and how uncertain is it
okay
um and one way to think about that is
you know if I if I plot the value on
this axis and the probability of
value on this axis you might have a node
where you're fairly convinced of the
value so that would be like the one over
here with 61 out of 100 you might have
another node whose mean is a little bit
lower
but has a much higher variance
because we haven't done so much sampling
and there's a good chance over here that
in fact that node is better even though
it's mean is lower because it has higher
variance there's a good chance that it's
actually better and so it's worth
allocating some more samples to this one
so you get a bonus for being uncertain
for having a low count
okay so uh this idea is implemented in a
heuristic called the UCB heuristic
um so this part is uh this is the total
utility this is the number of wins
you've got under the node n and this is
the number of samples you've tried for
node in so this is the win percentage
and that's how promising the node is and
this part I wouldn't worry too much
about the the log of the count of number
of samples that have gone through the
parent this is basically root one over n
and that's the standard deviation of uh
the the the mean basically so it's how
accurately have we estimated this mean
uh given this many samples and so you're
getting a bonus roughly proportional to
the standard deviation how much
uncertainty there is and you scale that
by some constant C and you have to
adjust C uh depending on the game and
maybe on the stage of the game
um but that's the basic idea
um and uh the UCB heuristic actually is
based on uh some in very interesting
Theory you can show that uh choosing
according to the UCB heuristic uh in
some sense does nearly as well as the
best possible policy uh that you could
have for choosing allocations in what
are called Bandit problems uh and Bandit
problems which you can look at further
in chapter 17
um or a very interesting class of
problems that uh that look at this
exploration exploitation or promising
versus uncertain trade-off unfortunately
uh this problem it doesn't happen to be
a bandit problem so all the theorems
about this UCB heuristic are completely
irrelevant uh and I think basically the
the people who invented MCTS just made a
mistake they weren't thinking straight
but nonetheless it actually still works
pretty well
okay there's one more thing that we want
to do which is to go beyond just
sampling from the root and actually as
we sample I use that to to start
building a tree so this is called UCT uh
which is the using the UCB or upper
confidence heuristic on trees
and the way it works
is that you take your current search
tree and you choose which Leaf node of
this tree I'm going to expand by
applying the UCB heuristic first at the
root to choose which child and then add
the child to choose which grandchild and
then at the grandchild to choose which
great grandchild and you do that until
you get to a leaf node and here a leaf
node is a node that is not yet fully
expanded
and then
having found such a leaf that means a
node that doesn't yet have all its
children added to the tree you add a new
child to that node and then you run a
rollout from that node C so I'm going to
illustrate this in a second so it
becomes clear
um and then you run the rollout you see
whether you win or lose and then you add
that win or loss to all of the win
counts right the win percentages on all
the nodes on the path back up to the
root and then you do that until you run
out of time so maybe you get to do 30
million rollouts altogether and then you
choose the action
that leads to the child that you visited
most often uh and we'll see in a second
why that uh why that makes sense
okay so let's um let's illustrate that
with a simple example so this is the
tree we've built so far um so you can
see that
um we tried uh one rollout each from
these two children
um but we lost uh and so uh uh We've so
far we've focused most of our effort on
this left Branch
um and we've explored three of its
children and done some roll out so we've
done
um three row Lots from here one from
there and two from there and there might
be a little more subtrees below that but
I'm not showing that
um
and uh and now if we apply the UCB
heuristic
um the UCB heuristic now says you know
what
um even though we lost that first time
the uncertainty remember you got this
bonus uh for the variance or the
standard deviation so that uncertainty
bonus uh can actually push up this node
above the above the UCB value of that
node
um and so we choose uh this one
um and now that's a leaf node so we add
a child we run a rollout from that node
uh in this case we win the rollout so if
this uh this node now has a count of one
uh one out of one
um we update the count for the parents
so it goes from zero out of one to one
out of two and then we update the uh the
count for the root so it goes up to five
out of 10. and then we start again and
we go back to the root we choose which
one whichever one UCB heuristic says to
choose and we keep going okay
um
and that's it so it's a very very simple
algorithm as I said it can it's very
easy to parallelize to give massive
parallelization
um to uh to get speed up using Modern
Hardware and
um
uh this revolutionized go programs in
the early 2000s and then what happened
with alphago was basically some some
improvements on this algorithm plus the
use of massive self-play uh to get very
good uh a very good rollout policies as
well as uh very good ability to evaluate
Leaf nodes which was a way of avoiding
doing uh loads and loads and loads of
rollouts because of computation costs
so you might ask okay well where's the
Min and Max right nowhere in this
algorithm did we do any men's or any
Maxes
okay and in fact this value of the node
if you think about it right the uh the
counts for a given node are basically
you know
the result of adding up the counts from
all the children so the value of a node
this this win percentage is in fact a
weighted sum of the win percentages of
the children
and it's weighted by uh how many times
you chose that particular child
so why is there no Min and why is there
no Max why how can you just do weighted
sums everywhere and expect to win even
in a deterministic game where you're
supposed to be doing mins and Maxes
right so the answer is that
as the number of samples become large
you will end up according to the UCB
heuristic right the the one over root n
goes to zero so your uncertainty Bonus
Goes to zero and you'll end up putting
all your rollouts into the best branch
okay and so as n goes to Infinity the
vast majority of rollouts are done on
the best child or if there's a tie the
two best children
um and so that means that this weighted
sum ends up being effectively converging
to Max or Min and there's a theorem
showing that as the total number of
rollouts for the tree goes to Infinity
the algorithm will play the Minimax move
even though it doesn't do any mins and
Maxes
um it's uh it's worth pointing out that
in reality of course not only does n not
go to Infinity but the the fringes of
the tree right the the deepest parts
that uh you've actually built tree uh
are always going to be a long way away
from being high-end or saturated uh and
so uh I think there might be uh ways of
improving this algorithm by uh by not
just backing up weighted sums but
actually uh slanting those in in a
maximum indirection
okay so to summarize a little bit over
time
um
we have uh
for the first time faced up to the fact
that we cannot make optimal decisions in
these games
um and the historical classical solution
is to do some kind of bound to depth
search with possibly some selection of
the search to put it in useful
directions
and to have a way of evaluating the leaf
nodes of the search using some
approximate kind of evaluation function
uh which could be a weighted feature
could be a big neural net or it could be
just doing roll-ups
um so the key thing is that you are
forced to make efficient use of the
computation resources that you have and
and in the course in the real world the
real world is so massively more complex
than any of these games uh that we
absolutely have to understand how to
make efficient use of computation
otherwise we are never going to get
anywhere in the real world so Alpha Beta
pruning was one way to make your
exploration of the tree more efficient
uh The Selective search in multicolored
research is another way
um but you could think of game playing
as like you know Formula One racing
um it might not be the real world but
because of this forcing function of
competition uh given limited resources a
lot of useful AI technology has come out
of it so reinforcement learning was
first developed by Arthur Samuel for
playing checkers uh iterative deepening
that we saw for search algorithms was
actually developed first for chess the
whole idea of meta reasoning of choosing
computations based on their ability to
improve your decisions was actually
developed in the context of Othello
this Monte Carlo research the idea of
random uh random look ahead or nearly
random look ahead to evaluate positions
uh actually came originally from some
work in chess but mainly was developed
for use in go
um we haven't talked about partial
information games and poker is uh the
sort of the classic partial information
game
um but in fact the the by far the best
algorithms for solving those kinds of
partial information games which are very
important in economics for example uh
bidding on on spectrums which is sort of
a hundred billion dollar auction uh
those algorithms were actually developed
for uh playing poker
um and oddly enough in fact the whole
probability theory was developed for
playing card games uh as well as uh
utility Theory
um so so there you go all right that's
it thank you very much
and uh I'll be doing Q a in real time
bye